Will Wittstruck

I'm passionate about Accessibility and User Experience (UX). For me, it's about all the customer contact points. By following WCAG accessibility and user-centered design principles, the experience should be: accessible to all, simple to use from beginning to end, and cohesive.



HIGHLIGHTS

Completed Training at Deque University on accessibility working towards certification with the International Association of Accessibility Professionals.

22+ years combined experience in User Experience (UX) layout & interaction design, usability, architecture, coding, plain talk writing, security, and video & audio production.

Mentoring, liaison, and documentation skills working with staff, stakeholders, vendors, and customers.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Full Stack Developer | SYE Productions

October 2001 – Present

As a Full Stack Developer, I provide the following services:

- Review websites for accessibility and usability issues.
- Troubleshoot code, validation errors, and display issues.
- Build websites for people and businesses from scratch or on top of a CMS.

I work with the client to develop a solution that works for them. I also provide training and documentation so they can manage their site:

- Designed used record store website to expand outreach to a global audience. This
 resulted in more sales world-wide.
- Designed cabin rental website to increase visibility/findability and improve number of days the cabin was rented. Created documentation and trained cabin owner on basic content updates.
- Designed and maintained musician website for 5+ years. Site gave the artist wider exposure and a way for fans and promoters to contact the musician.

Filmmaker | Year 51 Productions

June 2006 – Present

As co-founder of Year 51 Productions/4D4Films, I'm involved with every aspect of production from conception to release including: Project development, Writing, Planning, Directing, Cinematography, Editing, and Marketing

Our short films and videos have screened at the following events:

- Seattle True Independent Film Festival
- NW Projections Film Festival
- Rainier Independent Film Festival
- Plomondon Independent Film Festival
- Eugene Celebration Film Festival
- Hot Rod Monsters Film Festival
- EgoFest Short Film Festival
- Timberland Regional Library Teens Night

SKILLS

PHP/HTML/CSS/Sass

Troubleshooting

UI/UX design

Responsive design

Prototyping

Mentoring

Information architecture

Usability

Front-end development

Accessibility

Adobe Creative Cloud Suite

Quality assurance

JavaScript

WordPress

Video and Audio editing/mixing

EDUCATION

Associate Applied Sciences, Business Computer Systems

Spokane Community College, Spokane WA

Digital AccessibilityDeque University, Online

1700+ hours post college training online, classroom, and conferences.

AWARDS

2015 Best DMV website in the nation.

2013 Public Affairs and Community Education (PACE) Awards awarded by AAMVA.

Senior UX Engineer | Dept. of Licensing - Remote

May 2008 – June 2019

Designed, developed, and troubleshoot user interfaces across a variety of platforms, train and mentor team members, served as consultant and technical expert in the agency's mobile initiative.

- As member of Accessibility Workgroup, I assisted in developing agency accessibility policy, determining training needs, and documenting scope of work to get us in compliance and provide access to all customers.
- Retro-fitted dol.wa.gov (1,200+ pages) to be mobile-friendly and faster loading by 2-3 times, for all devices, in less than 1 week.
- Added dynamic content components to dol.wa.gov improving communication with our customers and simplifying maintenance.
- Performed and reported on usability testing for DOL websites & online services. Results led to changes that improved customer satisfaction and increased online transactions.
- Implemented Lean and Agile into daily work and projects resulting in many improvements. Results: Higher quality work far fewer defects. More work getting done. Measurable results.
- Worked with team to improve content and architecture for dol.wa.gov. This led to improved customer satisfaction rate of 78%.
- Mentored and cross-trained UX team and create documentation on CSS/SASS, PHP, HTML, database backup/restore, mobile design, and other process improvements.
- Published content updates to dol.wa.gov (public-facing site) and Inside Licensing (intranet). Ensure content is plain-talked and standardized before publishing.
- Provided tech support and customization of Inside Licensing WordPress site. Participated in state-wide CMS panel to share our experience with WordPress.

Systems Analyst/Programmer | Dept. of Labor & Industries - Olympia WA

January 2006 - May 2008

This position served as the Lead Systems Analyst and Application Programmer for Express Filing. Businesses used the system to file their State Fund quarterly report and pay industrial insurance premiums.

- Upgraded legacy front-end to follow W3C standards, enhance cross-browser stability, and improve usability.
- Actively participated in writing the budget decision package for 07-09 biennium that secured funding to improve Express Filing.
- Participated in planning and supporting migration of Express Filing to SecureAccess Washington gateway. This included direct customer support during the migration and programming maintenance.
- Provided legacy and project support during the transition to the new Express Filing system.

Technical Services Team Lead | Dept. of Personnel - Olympia WA

August 1999 - January 2006

This position was a "Jack of all trades" supporting Washington State's payroll system (mainframe and SAP), Intranet website, and Client server environment.

- Designed, tested and implemented HRMS (SAP) Security for HRMS Project.
- Provided training to Agency Security Administrators.
- Planned and participated in Disaster Recover Exercises for state's payroll system.
- Participated in the design, build and maintenance of Client Server environments.
- Assisted in design and implementation of Active Directory Groups for web publishing access. This improved and simplified maintenance and enabled single sign-on for access.
- Designed, built, and maintained HRISD's first intranet site. The site had the most common referenced documentation for staff.
- Analyzed and rebuilt payroll processing schedule to improve time. Original schedule took 8-10 hours and the new one took less than 2 hours.
- Served as database administrator, analyst, and job scheduling admin during successful Y2K project.

References available upon request.